But to me it's a backdrop.
So if only you could describe Nirvana,
what is that? What is your aim?
Your aim is Nirvana, what is it?
You mean if somebody uh Yeah, what is
Ni- gives that as an answer to a
question. Yeah.
What's it I'm aiming at Nirvana. Yeah.
Well, that's the thing, actually. Um
understanding correctly what Nirvana is,
means you would be at least a sotapanna.
Fully developing that understanding
means yeah, you you you have now
developed Nirvana as in became an
arahant. As to what it is, well, as the suttas
As to what it is, well, as the suttas
would describe it, it's absence of
greed, aversion, and delusion.
Complete absence in the sense of
the possibility of greed, aversion, or
or delusion is impossible.
So the mind has has has fully fully
understood it and fully
um got rid of it.
So it's not a place that one goes to.
No, exactly. It isn't.
It's not It's not a
It's not a magical realm that kind of
gets one enters upon if if if if upon
some certain
practice of a with meditation technique
or or something like that.
It's not a place you go into and replace
what you know with it.
It's really what you know now, your
experience as it is, what you have now,
remove greed, aversion, delusion, remove
possibility of greed, possibility of
aversion, possibility of delusion from
it. That's what
That's what
Nirvana becomes but that's what Nirvana
is.
That's why the Buddha said cooling down.
Literally. Cooling down of the fires of passion,
Cooling down of the fires of passion,
anger, and so on.
So you cool cool this thing down. This
experience, this life you have, you cool
it down
to the point of being
irreversible. It cannot go back and be entered again
It cannot go back and be entered again
by greed, aversion, or delusion. It's
been fully
fully frozen to the point of these three
things dying out and now they cannot
reappear. And that's that's that's a developed
And that's that's that's a developed
Nirvana.
So you can see that in order to cool
something down,
you need to have it, you need to
acknowledge it, you need to admit it,
you need to see
where the work in cooling it down lies.
You're not replacing it
with some with some new world, a new
realm, or new
new new new meditation experience.
You're actually fully understanding what
you already have. So you you don't need
anything new. Whatever you Whatever is
necessary for Nirvana, you already have
it. Everybody already has it.
Everybody already has it.
That's why the Buddha would refer to
element of Nirvana
in everyone's experience.
As in possibility of developing the
phenomenon which is Nirvana. It means
element of Nirvana is present.
It's not It's not about belief. It's not
No, no. And you see when people took it
as a belief, that's when they started
saying well we are already in Nirvana
cuz Nirvana is already there.
That's when you fail to see the
difference between a possibility and
like a actual development of something.
Yeah, Nibbana is there as a possibility.
But, saying that you have developed Nibbana
saying that you have developed Nibbana
means you need to have it as your actual
experience. As in you need to do the work of getting
As in you need to do the work of getting
rid of greed, aversion, delusion, ill
will, hatred, sensuality, all of that.
The Nibbana is the perfected
human being.
And it's a perfected human
Pretty much, but then see
perfected human being basically
it certainly a perfection,
uh but you wouldn't refer to that person
as a human being anymore.
Because human means going with the
nature, going with a with a with a grain,
going with a with a with a grain,
going with the current, going with
desires, going with with with the cravings and so
going with with with the cravings and so
on. That's what makes humans human.
Uh so you actually you cease to be a
human. Arahant is not human anymore.
If If the If that's the designation you
would use for a human.
But yeah, overall sure, as an individual
he still partakes as a as a being in the
human realm.
But really what what makes human human
are these things that you that you sort
of uh
undo and relinquish as an Arahant, as
somebody who's enlightened.
Overcoming your humanity. Well, pretty
much yeah. First you need to overcome
the immorality
and non-virtue.
But then you need to overcome that as
well. That's why you're not really
measurable by any human standards.
He's not like a good human or a bad
human, a good person or bad. No, he's
not a person anymore.
It's done.
He's abandoned, relinquished the
ownership of of of of the slightest sort of uh
of of of of the slightest sort of uh
appropriation of his own senses, his own
aggregates.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Nirvana Nirvana is
also called
the non what non-appropriation in
English in other Right. Yeah, yeah,
yeah. Sure. Sure. Non-appropriation.
Or the undetermined.
The undetermined, yeah.
Because the
things that are determined for a human
for an unenlightened unenlightened being
are things that are determined by greed,
aversion, delusion.
So, you remove that and there is nothing
determining things as mine anymore.
Hence, that experience is the
undetermined. The experience of the
undetermined.
But, it's a real experience as such.
That's why Nirvana is a thing, a
phenomena. A dhamma.
You can't really show people that
Nirvana. Can you show them? No. No. No,
of course not.
Well, you can
guide them to it, but even that will not
necessarily result in them getting to it
unless they have
made the effort themselves.
So, you can
point at it, you can describe it.
You can lay out the way that uh
that somebody can practice towards it,
but unless they practice
It's like It's like getting real.
Getting absolutely real. Sure.
Being honest with your situation.
It's up to me. It's not
Oh, yeah. Absolutely, yeah.
Well, not just being like being honest
with your situation, but also
recognizing the Buddha would refer to it as measure
the Buddha would refer to it as measure
the task.
Like a person would go and and and
listen to like a whatever somebody he
deems wise, somebody who he deems that
he can help him.
And then he would ponder on the meaning
of what's being said and what needs to
be done.
Once he starts grasping the meaning, he
can see, "Oh, okay, this is the amount
of effort. This is what I need to do."
So, like measure the task.
And that is absolutely necessary in
order to be able to do it.
But most people don't They kind of omit
that whole thing of, "Hold on, what does
this actually mean?"
It might make me feel good. It's might
making me It's might It's It's might be
very inspiring for me, but do I
understand what it means?
When I read the sutta or when I face
instruction that sort of directing me
towards nibbana, am I aware of of of the
actual uh meaning of it as in like what exactly
uh meaning of it as in like what exactly
I need to do?
And And most people are not encouraged
to think like that. So, it's most like,
"Okay, you're inspired. That's great.
Now, here is a meditation technique
which you just do mechanically, and then
the experience you have,
if it's if it's um
substantial enough as in like if it if
it affects you
uh significantly enough, then we can
interpret it as nibbana or as something
leading to nibbana. But nibbana is not
an interpretation.
Any Any basically Any Any part of developing
Any basically Any Any part of developing
of wisdom
does not partake in interpretation.
Certainly not by external terms.
It partakes in direct understanding of
the meaning of it,
which then results in direct freedom
from suffering. And hence, that's the
greatest verification of your wisdom.
You know you're right cuz you cannot
suffer amidst suffering.
amidst suffering.
You cannot engage in ill will. You
cannot engage in sensuality.
You cannot engage in craving or
distraction or delusion.
And And even if the whole world says,
"No, that's wrong."
you know that they are wrong because you
are the one free from suffering.
That's why arahant
um anagami, sakadagami, sotapanna
basically They are the ones they go Well, arahant
They are the ones they go Well, arahant
is completely developed against the
grain. Against the grain of nature and the
Against the grain of nature and the
outputs of the mind and intentions and
cravings and feelings and so on.
Sotapanna is somebody
who got got the He understood it. He
understood what that is, but he hasn't
fully developed it. He hasn't fully went
upstream, so to speak.
Because it's as I said, it's not like a
a theory or ideology that you are sort
of
uh
justifying and making it like an
argument proof or something. No, it's a
directly verify verifiable in your
experience. Why? Because you have the
criteria. Suffering and freedom from it.
Sensuality and freedom from it. Ill will
and freedom from it. So, you're free
from those things not because you've
been running away from those things or
you've been hiding or or or sort of
trying to manage the circumstances so
you don't get challenged externally. No,
you're free from those things because
amidst those things the mind cannot be
overwhelmed by them. So, you don't
engage. It's not even a matter of restraint
It's not even a matter of restraint
anymore. It becomes impossible once
understanding has fully taken place. It
becomes impossible to suffer amidst
suffering. And as I said, that that is the
And as I said, that that is the
the greatest verification a person can
have that they've been practicing rightly.
Is there verification from others?
Saying No, of course not. No.
No, of course not. No.
Well, then. No.
I mean,
the others can verify it as they did in
the sutras basically not by
yes, I see the magic blue light aura
around his head, he is an arahant.
But by talking to that person,
interrogating them to the point of
discerning the the subtle meanings and
they were like, "Yeah." Cuz an arahant
would know what another arahant needs
has to have understood beforehand.
So, he would know that, which means
through questioning he could see the
extent of other person's understanding.
And that's that's that was also a way of
progress as well.
The Buddha would often encourage that in
the suttas, saying the monks would sort
of interrogate each other, not like for
the sake of argument, but for the sake
of pressing for the meaning.
You wouldn't leave anything unturned.
So, you'd be drilling and delving, and
basically making effort to understand,
and then being questioned by your
What's the translation? By spiritual
companions and so on. Again, it's like
have you understood this? Have you
understood? And if you thought you did,
well, you will then be able to to convey
it to somebody else who did understand
it. But then again, if you if you thought
But then again, if you if you thought
you did, but you haven't, this
questioning can actually spur you to to
make further effort, cuz you realize,
"Oh, okay. I haven't been considering
this or that or whatever the questions
contain."
But again, you can see that most of the
modern practice today, when it comes to
Buddhist meditation, has nothing to do
with it.
It's just watch your nostrils, cross
your legs, sit in lotus, and and and
that's it, and it will happen, whatever.
Yeah, from what you just said, it seems
that discussing discussing
the Dhamma
is useful.
Go on. Shall I finish the sentence?
Yeah, discussing the Dhamma is useful,
provided that at least one of those
people has understood it.
Otherwise, it's blind leading the blind.
In other words, two analyzing person who
who people who hasn't who haven't even
understood uh what sotapatti is,
uh what sotapatti is,
they can discuss the Dhamma all they
want.
It won't result in knowledge, as in like
you pair two ignorances together, it's
not going to amount to knowledge.
Because puthujjana's experience is
top-to-bottom ignorance.
So, you cannot accidentally stumble upon
or even find a right reference
towards that ignorance. That's what the
Buddha said, the absolutely necessary
condition for arising of the right view
is utterance of another, of another who
has understood it.
And paired with that, they need to have
the right attention as in they need to
know basically how to hear it, not to
dismiss it, how to attend to it, and how
to practice that right utterance.
So then, once see like for like for
example, two sotapannas could
enable each other better in practice if
they were to discuss it. Cuz it would
just be reminding them of what they
already know, but they haven't pressed
it far enough in terms of understanding.
Or even better, sotapanna talking to an
arahant. But puthujjana talking to puthujjana, it
But puthujjana talking to puthujjana, it
can only remain puthujjana.
Or or be dealing with uh
mundane terms.
Well, exactly. Yeah, it might be it
might be it might be uh helping each
other how to manage the suffering
better. But sotapatti is not management of
But sotapatti is not management of
suffering, it's the first step of
uprooting it.
As in you know exactly how to uproot it,
and that's already freedom from
suffering, you know, to a great degree.
So what about uh speech, truthful
speech?
Right speech. Mhm.
Would you say so you wouldn't say that
discussing the Dhamma or your your your concerns,
the Dhamma or your your your concerns,
your spiritual concerns,
with other people who are also on the
same kind of path
you wouldn't say that's
right or or
What?
noble. Well, if if you define noble by by that
Well, if if you define noble by by that
which pertains to like sort of about
your higher, then it isn't, of course.
Now, it can help people because
in a sense of
uh
it can it can make them make the effort
on the personal level further.
By having an intelligent feedback, even
if it's an ordinary person. What they
should not expect is that the
conversation, the discussion itself
results in some great epiphany.
But in the in the same sense you come
across a new sort of or you come across
other wrong view that then you actually
understand better and by doing so you
clarify what the right view is.
So, of course, that's all thanks to
their personal effort
towards understanding
the nature of suffering and freedom from
it. But yes, if if there is if the other
person is equally sort of striving as
you are, then that discussion can sort
of just
well, at least hint at certain
directions.
of of your of your reflection and of
your contemplation. Good.
Both of those people say, "Well, I'm not
enlightened. Are you enlightened?" "No,
I'm not enlightened." So, it's two
unenlightened, honest, unenlightened
Well, now there yeah, exactly. There is
a difference between that. You have
sometimes people debating just because
it's pleasant. "Hey, let's have a
discussion about it and just bounce
ideas off each other." Well, I mean,
that's that's utterly pointless.
But if you know your situation that
you're an ordinary person, and you know
that nothing sort of super mundane so to
speak can come out of this discussion
with another ordinary person. But you do
it just to highlight your ignorance
further, which means you did begin with that
which means you did begin with that
self-honest attitude.
But in that same sense, you don't even
need the other person. Just pick up any
philosophy book and look at it like,
"Okay, this is supposedly the wrong
view. But have I understood it, why, and to
But have I understood it, why, and to
what extent, and where exactly it's
wrong?" So, by that no So, you're not looking
So, by that no So, you're not looking
for faults. You're genuinely adopting
that view in order to be able to
understand the extent of it.
And by doing so, that's why often the
Buddha would describe all these wrong
views that were present at the time.
Because by fully understanding their
extent, one would be much closer to the right
one would be much closer to the right
view.
So, as I said, discussing with another
equally intelligent, equally
self-transparent person, that can help.
Still making noise.
That can help in the same sense that
reading reading other books or other
teachings can help.
But not if you if you don't have that
necessary um
self-transparent basis.
Come here.
It's okay. Come here.
It's okay.
That's it. Good boy.
So, ideally, you want to be at
discussing these things with a
sotapanna, someone who has
Exactly. Yeah. understood the Dhamma.
Yeah, then you can you Yeah, yeah, cuz
otherwise, I think it is just stabbing
in the dark. And even if YOU ACTUALLY DO
EVEN IF YOU DO ACTUALLY STAB SOMETHING,
you wouldn't know it.
So, that that's what I mean. Like, hey,
you can you can you can profit from it
if you're already very self-transparent
in the same sense you would profit from
reading other other views, other things,
because you do have self-transparency.
So, you're not looking for faults,
you're not covering it up, you haven't
just adopted a belief that this is
wrong, but you're genuinely
understanding the extent of it and why
it's wrong and how it's wrong.
So, for a person who's
who wants to discuss with a sotapanna,
what how can he find one? Well, exactly.
He has no reference. What is his
criteria? Well, that this is what his
criteria is Well, the closest to the
right criteria can get is this
self-transparency, being honest with
oneself. And not not being dismissive of of other
And not not being dismissive of of other
views, even if they are not pleasing to
you. Cuz usually people's criteria
Cuz usually people's criteria
uh for their views, opinions,
ideologies, beliefs is basically
emotional. This is pleasing to me
This is pleasing to me
for whatever. There is maybe
a a a small kind of degree of
uh
reasoning involved, but mostly just This
is emotionally pleasing to me, thus this
is my view, and that's why I'm defending
it. And that's why I'm criticizing other
And that's why I'm criticizing other
views.
Not because I have understood my view or
I understood other views. No, it's just
because circumstantially I adopted it,
and now I'm defending it at all cost.
So, that that attitude is cannot That
attitude is is a is a is a basically the
main impediment. That's like the wrong
attention. When when one looks And the Buddha said
When when one looks And the Buddha said
they're looking for faults in a speaker
will prevent you understanding what he
means. And by not getting the meaning, then you
And by not getting the meaning, then you
might actually sort of cross over a a
sotapanna or even an arahant who's been
speaking, you've been listening to it,
but you were not paying
uh proper attention, as in you were
dismissing it or or or not listening to
carefully enough, and that's it. It's
gone, and your views, your wrong views,
your wrong criteria remained unaffected.
Which means you're not not advised not
advised even by like having a Buddha
himself in front of you teaching you.
So, that's what I mean. If you're
self-transparent, honest with yourself,
so you know your situation, you know
that you're not free from suffering, not
free from sensuality or greed or
aversion, and then you also recognize the
and then you also recognize the
inevitability of having to have some
views, but you don't judge
but you don't judge
uh you don't judge your situation
through your views, you judge your views
through a situation.
As in you can't help having views, but
at the same time you recognize, well,
I'm not free from suffering, I'm not
free from greed, aversion, delusion. I'm
not a sotapanna, basically. Which means
the views that I do hold and regard
there, I should put in question.
Because it's because of those very views
that I am not free from suffering, free
from greed, aversion, delusion. I'm not
a sotapanna yet.
But people might think one thing, then
they might think about the the second
thing of their views, but they never put
it together and see that that's a
contradiction. Cuz you can't have
puthujjana's views that are right and
not be a sotapanna.
Cuz right view means sotapatti. So, if
if you if you don't have the right view,
you can't then entertain the notion that
you're puth- sorry, if you're not a
puthujjana if you're not a sotapanna, if
you're a puthujjana, you can't entertain
a notion that you also have right views.
And their attitude is unpleasant.
Because it's like living in perpetual
doubt of your own existence, and that's
that's very can be very anxious,
very Yeah, full like lots quite lots of lots
Yeah, full like lots quite lots of lots
of sort of concern, because any single
view that then you you look into, you
realize, well,
this might be wrong.
Then any confidence that you might have
had as a puthujjana get completely
undone, demolished. But that's the whole
point. So, that's why when the practice of
So, that's why when the practice of
Dhamma when when when when the when
thinking and reflecting upon views, it's
not optional anymore. It's existential,
basically. You need to do it. You need to clarify
You need to do it. You need to clarify
it, cuz you realize the peril of it.
You can't just simply adopt a belief
that's
Well, you can adopt a belief, but if you
are if you are self-honest, if you do
have that honesty,
uh you wouldn't be able to.
As as appealing as a belief might be,
you wouldn't be able to um
Well, you would be able to at the
expense of honest self-honesty.
But, if you realize that self-honesty
should not be compromised ever,
then uh that's your safeguard against
adopting and proliferating things just simply
and proliferating things just simply
upon a belief.
So, then if you adopt something, it
would be after heavy scrutiny.
And even then, you wouldn't adopt it as
a belief.
You would adopt it pretty much as a
strategy towards your practice of of of of uh
towards your practice of of of of uh
freedom from suffering.
Which means if that strategy is not
bearing any fruit,
and you're not free from suffering,
you're going to be upgrading it or
changing it, and you won't be afraid to
do it. And faith?
And faith?
Well, that's Yeah. See, you can have
You can't have a belief without faith,
but you can have a faith without a
belief. So, the faith that we are talking about
So, the faith that we are talking about
is the is the I think it's in the sutras
it's mentioned in my I might have spoken
about it before. The faith we're talking
about is the faith that you would have
that a person would have in a in a
doctor. As in, you recognize your situation
As in, you recognize your situation
through that self-honest scrutiny of
yourself, basically.
You recognize that you need help, as in,
you are a subject to suffering, you are
prey to suffering, you don't know the
way out from a reason suffering.
And then you find something that
promises a way out. So, you have faith
that it might work.
If it's applied, obviously.
So, in the same sense, you recognize you
have a an illness, you go to a doctor,
so you have faith that he can help you,
that he can prescribe you medicine,
and then whatever
uh uh uh course of treatment or
something, that will then result in in
that freedom. Now,
from that element. So, if you do start
taking medicine and doing everything
rightly, you understood doctor's
instructions properly,
and you're not being free from your
ailment, well, maybe you have faith a
bit longer, a bit more, keep applying
it. But then if it's nothing, there's no
results, well, then you won't have a problem
well, then you won't have a problem
changing it,
looking for a different way because it's
not working. You haven't done it out of
a sort of um emotional attitude or you
nothing No, you really you genuinely
tried and it had it didn't free you. But
if it does free you, then that faith
disappears because you have you don't
have to have faith that it will work
because now you know that it worked and
you're a cure. cured
And that's when the sutras like for
sotapanna, his faith in the Buddha
Dhamma Sangha has been replaced by the
confirmed confidence.
So, it was confirmed. Now he can see he
can see his health
as a direct result of having faith in
this application.
But again,
you need to be honest because if you're
not, you're going to be blaming a
doctor. You're going to be blaming the one who
You're going to be blaming the one who
gave the instruction.
But actually, you first need to start
with yourself.
Cuz if it's not working, if you don't
have patience, if it's not working
quickly Well, if you don't have patience
and you're not self-transparent, you
won't see that you're impatient.
So, then you won't see that it's
actually your lack of patient
patience that's a problem.
Um as in you need to take the medicine a
bit longer. And then you're just going
to dismiss the doctor
who could have been Buddha himself.
So, that's why I insist always on like
like self-transparency because if you're
not, you will be pointing fingers,
basically, when there are no results to show for.
So the instructions given by the Buddha
What are they? What do you What was his
first instructions?
What was his first things he did?
What was the first thing he did? There's
suffering and there's freedom from it.
Because you have
What are you recording, yeah?
The Buddha only gives precepts much
later on
in his
during his life. Much later on. Well, he
he he he defines them specifically later
on. But
Yeah. The the actual virtue that was
sort of contained in the eight precepts
has been praised by him throughout the
sutras in Digha Nikaya, Majjhima Nikaya.
Like he would say that the wise men of
the past were virtuous and so he was
just he was taking for granted basically
that somebody who has already came to
that point of practicing the Dhamma has
already had their virtue developed.
They've been restrained, moral,
virtuous, honest, and so on. Where did
they get those
uh that morality from? Who?
The people who In the past?
Yeah. Well, from understanding the
natural principles, as in the universal
principles of uh of uh of a human
existence.
Okay. So, understanding
principles. Okay.
Okay.
Yeah. Say, if you if if Well, basically,
yeah, if you understand why is um
virtue virtuous,
that's already the beginning of wisdom.
So, you can also arrive at that
understanding by taking virtue on faith,
the faith we discussed.
So, if faith that virtue is necessary in
the same sense the doctor says you tells
you, "Well, this medicine will work
only if you follow a strict diet.
If you careless with what you eat, it's
going to cancel the the the the uh
effectiveness of uh of uh of a
prescription I'm giving you."
But, obviously, some people will not
have even that little bit of faith, but
if they do investigate,
reflect upon themselves in a in that
same uh transparent manner, well, you
would see basically that uh
virtue is virtuous cuz it does not
contain any existential discrepancy or
contradiction.
Which means in order to arrive at it,
you are already developing wisdom.
Like, good things are good because they
they're basically
aligned with the universal uh
principles, with things that are most fundamental.
with things that are most fundamental.
So, like, for example,
sharing and giving and charity is good.
Like, why? Well, people say, "Oh, it
makes me feel good." That's all
secondary. Existentially, charity is
good because it goes a line
sorry goes along the way of you not
being owner of the things in the first
place. Yet everybody starts with a sense of
Yet everybody starts with a sense of
ownership. It's completely gratuitous,
but everybody owns. Everybody
immediately feels that they're owner of
their body, their senses. Basically
through engagement with the world
through the tools which are your senses,
which is your body, you you start you
fully identified with the tools.
With eye, nose, nose, ears, and the
mouth, body, and everything else
basically. So you don't know why, but they said
So you don't know why, but they said
giving is good. Well, giving is good cuz
you basically deprive yourself of
something to give to somebody else which
resembles the experience of
non-ownership of that which has been
owned. That which I still regard as mine, I
That which I still regard as mine, I
give to somebody else.
So you can arrive at it either through
doing that and then contemplating it or
not doing it, but then you need to have
discerned it, but it's highly unlikely
you're going to arrive at it through
stinginess and uh
and and uh and complete sort of uh lack
of any any virtue, a basis of virtue.
Or or or or or or charity and kindness.
And you can you can take any any other
thing that's regarded as good and
virtuous genuinely.
You would see that it would be along the
it would be mirroring, it would be
reflecting upon some some principles
of your existence
that you're living right there and then,
but you're not aware of.
Lying, basically, it's another
discrepancy. There is a truth, you choose to override
There is a truth, you choose to override
it.
You choose to act upon that discrepancy.
And then perpetuate it as a
non-discrepancy. And that's why it's unwholesome. Same
And that's why it's unwholesome. Same
stealing.
It reinforces the that perverted pattern
of human existence as in I'm the owner
of my body and my senses and things that
I can gain through. To the point of then
taking that which you perceive through
your senses as not yours.
As an extension of the very attitude
that you have towards your own senses.
Cuz basically you do become a thief. We
might have all started as as borrowing.
We're all just just just basically
renting this body and these senses, so
to speak. They're given to us for our
use. But the moment you start regarding
as yours that which you have rented, you
have effectively stolen it.
Taken from Mara. Exactly. Yeah.
Yeah, the Buddha did say that. He said,
"Because people
take and use that which doesn't belong
to them,
uh well, they take it as theirs that
which doesn't belong to them. That's why
the Mara controls them and does what he
wants and that's why they're subject to
suffering and the whole
uh
death and misery and everything else."
And then when when when the monks asked,
"So, what are those things?" He said,
"It's I eyes and the objects, ears and
sounds, nose and smells, mouth uh sorry,
tongue and tastes, body and touches."
Those are the things basically that
don't belong to you. They you're just
renting. They're just borrowed uh
borrowed jewelry as the Buddha would
refer to you.
But you start entertaining the notion
that you are their owner, they are they
are their own.
And it's not it's not a like a
metaphysical secret
that you need to figure out in order to
drop it, to to not regard it as yours.
No, you just need to dwell on the fact
that they're not yours.
Just need to keep really really really
investigating the meaning of not mine.
And then applying it to yourself.
And then obviously in the most general
terms, that's what the Buddha would
describe like, "Well, if you were the
owner of your body, for example, would
that body be subjected to sickness,
aging, and death? It wouldn't.
See, many people think they Oh, yeah, of
course I understand that. I'm subject to
all these things. But, if you truly
understood If you were to truly
understand that, you would be completely
free from appropriation.
So, that's what I mean. If you're
self-transparent, then you would see a
discrepancy. On one hand, I'm thinking I
understood it.
On another hand, I don't have that which
is supposed to be the result of that
understanding, as in freedom from
appropriation, freedom from suffering,
freedom from greed, aversion, delusion.
And if you see that discrepancy, that
contradiction, then you'll know exactly
where to do the work.
Which is, okay, I need to understand
this further, and what I think
understanding is, it's not sufficient.
Or sometimes it's just plain out wrong.
But, you have You haven't You You
wouldn't have seen it unless you brought
brought this discrepancy like to the
fore, fully understood it.
So, initially one takes on virtue
given ex- given from an external
Well, yeah, exactly. Set of values or
whatever. But, you could see that in
every society there is a degree of it
because it would kind of seep down
into like, you know, collective society
awareness that's sort of among the like
completely unenlightened people, but
you'd still get the sense of it. Sharing
is good, patience is good, all these
things. It is good, but it's also good to
It is good, but it's also good to
understand why these things are good.
Cuz then you can take it even further.
Then you Yeah, you can discover virtue
by yourself.
Yeah, I suppose. Well, the Buddha did,
so yeah, you could say that the Buddha
did discover it by himself.
But, it it's it's
it's highly unlikely cuz you would kind
of need some pointers, some external
reference points.
bit deeper without having Yeah.
Well, you can you can only take it so
far, basically. You could discover
virtue by yourself to a degree, but not
to the to the not fully understand it to
the point of becoming a sotapanna
as in the one who has understood sila
and thus he's free from silabbata
paramasa, which is virtue and duty.
Fetter of virtue and duty he's free
from. Cuz that's that's another thing.
Cuz that's that's another thing.
In order to understand virtue, you need
to have it.
You can't be a non-virtuous person and
then understand the nature of virtue.
You need to be having it present in your
presently risen experience. As in you
need to be virtuous, basically.
But being virtuous in itself, it's nice,
but it does not result in wisdom. And if
there's no wisdom, there's no
liberation. That's why obviously sila and virtue,
That's why obviously sila and virtue,
it's not the dhamma,
but that's why also dhamma is impossible
to arise without sila. Cuz how can you
understand How can you develop
understanding of sila without sila?
Impossible. But many people don't see that
But many people don't see that
connection, which is why that is the
very first fetter of silabbata paramasa.
People think you must be virtuous and
yes, you do. You do have to be virtuous.
But then they think, "Okay, so I'm doing
that and now the practice of dhamma and
understanding is over here.
I'm doing my meditation technique. I'm
reading the suttas. I'm studying Pali
and I'm virtuous. So it's all
contributing." No.
Basically, you have the virtue.
You have the morality. You have the
restraint. You take it even further and practice
You take it even further and practice
like the sense restraint even of things
that are not necessarily non-virtuous,
but are not virtuous enough, perhaps.
Such as pursuing sight, sound, smell,
taste, touches that are distracting.
They're not necessarily rooted in anger
and breaking of um moral precepts or
rooted in sensuality and breaking
celibacy precepts and so on, but they
can be rooted in distraction distraction
and carelessness. You stop doing that
and then you understand that very basis.
You don't need to go elsewhere.
You don't need some other like whatever
developing or some sort of
uh supramundane concentration. No, you
already have it in front of you. Now you
need to start making the effort to cut
through that fog of of of of ignorance
in regard to it.
Don't just take it for granted that it's
good. Understand it. Why it is good.
That's why the definition of sotapanna
is he's the one who knows good as good
and bad as bad. Putujana is like a
virtuous putujana, a good putujana is
the one who doesn't know good as good,
bad as bad.
So if you do want to practice meditation
and contemplation, practice it within
the basis of your virtuous behavior and
sense restraint.
Not left, right, before, or after it.
Within it. As in when this this is.
When the very basis of virtue is
present, me trying to understand it is
also present.
But the point is to understand that they
are not found elsewhere or they are not
given to you through some sort of
um
divine providence, through some sort of
uh
super concentration you developed and
then you have this great revelation.
You develop it on the basis that you
maintain. So you're maintaining the basis of
So you're maintaining the basis of
virtue
and then you develop your understanding
of it.
That's it.
And that's why for sotapanna who's
understood the nature of virtue, who's
understood good as good, bad as bad,
all he needs to do is continue
practicing uh nekkhamma sankappa as in the video we
uh nekkhamma sankappa as in the video we
described it.
Renunciation. Thoughts of renunciation, basically. So
Thoughts of renunciation, basically. So
being virtuous and sense restraint and
practicing thoughts of renunciation and
that will that in itself will then
result in arahantship cuz he has
understood that.
So through doing it, he's developing
that very understanding of it.
And that's how you would also, as the
Buddha would often
encourage people to see the danger in
the slightest fault.
That's how you would start seeing the
danger in the slightest fault.
Oh, it's just a small thing. Doesn't
matter. Big thing or small thing, if it
partakes in the nature of unwholesome,
it's unwholesome. Thus, it's directly
against the principle of Dhamma, the
universal principles.
And that's why it would be enough for
somebody to receive
instruction as simple as avoid anything
that's unwholesome and cultivate
anything that's wholesome.
As they did in the suttas,
the the Buddha's foster mother,
when she asked for that instruction.
And the Buddha said, "Look, anything you
know that's unwholesome, abandon it. And
anything you know that's wholesome,
cultivate." And then she went for like
seclusion for 3 months and so on and
came back an arahant. Fully enlightened.
Fully enlightened.
Fully freed, basically. Cuz she fully
understood it.
And you could see how many people today
Oh, yeah, of course, this is bad, this
is good.
But if you were to truly understand
that, you'd be a sotapanna. So, then, if
you think you know have a knowledge of
what's good, what's bad,
ask yourself, are you a sotapanna? Are
you a stream-enterer?
If the answer is no, then don't take
that knowledge for granted.
Because it's not sufficient. I mean, it
might be good and sufficient for mundane
terms. But for instance, I might be I might be
But for instance, I might be I might be
a sotapanna. Yeah, that's Well, exactly.
If you might be means you're not free
from another
fetter, which is in that first group,
which is fetter of doubt. If you don't
know you're a sotapanna, it means you're
not sotapanna.
Understanding what sotapanna is makes
you one.
Understanding what silabbata paramasa is
from it.
Understanding what a self view is
frees you from it.
So you guys say, "I might be free from
self view, but I don't know it yet."
Means you're not.
I mentioned yesterday when I was talking
to those people, um
with I don't want to mention names. Uh
Well, this this whole like like
self-reflexive attitude is like
you really want to do it
in order to gain wisdom. To learn from
it, basically.
You don't want to be eight.
You're not doing it because you want to
you want to justify your actions. I
mean, that's how people usually be doing
it.
I'm not going to say it again. Yo.
Yo.
And the Oh.
Yeah. Crazy little one.
Crazy little one.
Crazy little one. Calm down now.
Calm down now.
You really want to ask yourself,
basically. Like say when it comes to practice of
Like say when it comes to practice of
dhamma, why are you doing it?
Like really clarify
what where do you want to arrive with
it? What what's the goal?
And just or in general, in any any areas
of your life, basically. Just ask
yourself, "What do I want to do with my
life? What what is my purpose?"
But don't ask and expect immediate
answers something like that, but ask and
then think about it.
think about it.
And then if the answer presents itself,
well then question that answer.
Cuz most people
would would be
would be going through life basically
like what they I don't know if there's
an English expression, but certainly
back in Serbia like a headless fly.
Headless chicken. Well, you know, like a
fly that that doesn't have and it's just
flying like mad left and right hitting
into windows. It's still flying, but it
doesn't have the head so it doesn't see
where anymore. Mhm.
And and and most people would actually
be able to help themselves if they just
just stop for a second and ask yourself
like why why am I doing this particular
thing? What for?
Why do I want it? What do I want?
Most people don't even know what they
want. So they're just like habitually
So they're just like habitually
scratching the itch
like an um animal basically and going
through things as they arise.
So the attitude would help even in terms
of like a ordinary lay life, somebody
who's not interested in in greater
development of the dharma or something.
But let alone for somebody who does want
to practice dharma, it's just completely
necessary. You need to develop that
self-reflection, that transparency, and
that kind of
um scrutiny of your own self, of your
own thoughts, of your own intentions.
Cuz it will force
the correct perspective upon you. You
can't have it willingly. You can't just
willingly adopt the correct perspective.
Cuz any perspective you know of, it's
already a perspective that's affected by
greed, aversion, delusion.
So just just ask yourself, where where
do I where do I where do I want to be
in say
in 1 year's time or 2 years' time
provided I live that long. And what's
what's my purpose? What's my goal?
Or ask like you can basically review
things that you already got committed to
or engaged in and just like, well,
why am I doing this? Why am I still
doing this?
Why did I start doing this?
And see what the answers come up.
I want to be successful.
Okay, so what for?
Say I'm doing this job because I want to
earn money and be my own boss. Why Why
is
Why is that a good thing, being your own
boss? Why is that something you value?
Well, the answer would be because it's
unpleasant to have somebody else telling
me what to do.
Okay, so why is then the unpleasant
experience of having somebody else tell
you what to do?
Why is that a problem for you
on the personal level?
Why can't you just remain indifferent
towards the economies
and just do it? Why is it a problem?
Well, it's a problem because it's making
me suffer.
Ah, so suffering is a problem. So now,
you're doing this job 10 hours a day,
earning loads of money, trying to start
your own business,
just because you don't so you don't
suffer. But is there a guarantee
But is there a guarantee
that you won't suffer after all that
effort you put in? There isn't.
And then secondly, that all effort you
put in, you might have overcome
possibility of suffering on account of
somebody else telling you what to do,
but there are millions of other ways of
suffering in your life.
Which means you invested your
like your whole life, how many years of
building something up just to address
like 0.1% of possibilities of suffering?
You haven't freed yourself from the
nature of suffering.
You've only freed yourself from one
particular manifestation of it.
Having somebody else
less qualified than me telling me what
to do and bossing me around.
Is that a Is that a fair investment? Is
that a good investment?
You realize it isn't. So then obviously
the inevitable question is well, what do
I do then?
Well, you ask yourself what's more
important.
Being completely free from suffering or
partially. Now you can choose whatever
you want, but choose it then you will
choose it choose it responsibly.
Because now you know, okay, there is a
possibility of being free from suffering
all together.
But I feel it feels a bit daunting for
me. So
So
I'm kind of satisfied with sort of
halfway. But that's fine, but then you would take
But that's fine, but then you would take
responsibility for it, which means when
the other half of suffering that you
haven't freed yourself comes your way,
you won't be blaming others, you won't
be resorting to ill will,
psychologizing your suffering, finding
excuses for it. No, you'll accept it as
part of the deal that you accepted when
you clarified your perspective and your
goals. But if you haven't done that,
But if you haven't done that,
everything will always be someone else's
fault and you're not going to be
responsible for anything you do, yet
you're going to be equally bound, even
more probably, with suffering and you
won't be able to do anything about it.
Which means your efforts are completely
misdirected, yet that was the goal from
the start.
And now for somebody who does practice
Dharma, just again ask yourself, well,
why am I practicing Dharma? To be free
from suffering. Well, is my current way
of practicing, is it is it contributing?
Well, yeah, I hope it is, but do you
know for sure that it is?
Well, it must. Well, that's that's not
the right answer. It must be
contributing cuz I've been doing it for
20 years.
If it's contributing,
means your suffering is lessening. Means
possibility to suffer is being being
lessened, being fading out.
So you need to be honest and admit
because the answer might not be a
pleasing one, especially if you invested
20 years in practice and you still can't
tell whether you're you're you're you're
anything closer to being free from
suffering. But that is the absolute necessary step,
But that is the absolute necessary step,
for as long as you ignore to to address
it in such direct, non-compromising
manner, you can be practicing for hundreds of
you can be practicing for hundreds of
years
and still remain a puthujjana.
And sometimes, all it would take for you
to stop being puthujjana is that.
Just admit that you are puthujjana.
It doesn't like because some people
might have actually done the right
practice, but they don't know it.
But, they can only find out once they
admit that they don't know it.
And then if it were right, their
efforts, their reflection, then they're
Oh, yeah.
But, because they are too afraid to go
that way,
they'll never find out. And that's why
they won't be an arahant.
And that's why it's their great loss.
Basically, all your efforts
remain undermined
just by lacking that last grain of
courage. Just admitting to yourself
Just admitting to yourself
that you don't know.
Truly. On that existential level.
Even after so many years of practice, of
so-called practice. Yeah.
Of trying to. Yeah.
It's supposed like someone trying to
get rich
and then pretending that they are
already rich after 10 years.
rich after 10 years.
It is a again, it's another discrepancy.
That's what I mean. Like, arahant is
completely 100% discrepancy free. Any
discrepancy in the existential is
impossible. That's the definition
That's the definition
of an arahant.
So, if you start recognizing that, you
would see exactly, yeah. So, I'm I'm I'm
I'm practicing
or I'll say I'm I'm I'm I'm working to
be rich, but I'm not rich.
So, I can be blaming others
or I can accept others as a factor in me
not being rich and then incorporate it
in my efforts.
And then upgrade my efforts.
But only once I admit that I'm poor.
If you don't admit it, yeah, it'll be
everybody else's fault
that's preventing you from getting there
or whatever.
Uh and you keep you're still going to be
doing the same things because of which
you're not getting where you want to
get.
So you won't be questioning your efforts
of getting rich, acquiring wealth
uh despite your immediate poverty.
So is there like a time period that one
can say
you can you can try a certain Well,
that's where we we go back to the very
first thing we said about the faith. And
then yeah. So you have to have some
faith and you have to give it some time.
But yeah, after a while you might even
have to cut your losses and just
restart.
Because you're not doing it for the sake
of doing it, you're doing it to be free
from suffering. You're doing it for the
goal. You're doing it for the fruit. You're
You're doing it for the fruit. You're
doing it to arrive at that at that
degree of liberation. But obviously
But obviously
somewhere down the line for some people
that kind of got pushed in the
background and now
they became too precious, too protective
of the efforts they invested
in their practice
despite the lack of result.
the lack of result.
And then they defend that. They defend
that kind of indefensible position, really.
kind of indefensible position, really.
It's a contradiction.
But they say, "Well,
I might not be a social planner, but
surely all these efforts could not have
been wasted."
And they refuse to let go of it. And
then but that means they have to keep
doing it.
Cuz if they change their effort, that
would be almost like an affirmation, the
fact that they've been wasting
that they've been misguided and and
misdirecting their efforts. So then they
have to stick it just to keep validating
it for themselves that they are not
wrong. And because of that, they get becoming
And because of that, they get becoming
more and more wrong with each time.
Cuz that that transparency, if it were
there to begin with, got completely
obscured.
So, basically, question yourself and be
honest. And don't fabricate. Don't push for
And don't fabricate. Don't push for
answers.
Just be honest.
Where am I at with my practice?
Am I Am I complacent?
Do I think I have time as in how long
will I live?
All these things.
And you read the suttas, that's
that's all the time he's talking about.
And how how And you don't do it for some
sort of
gaining some sort of emotional kind of
uplifting. No, you're doing it for
understanding.
You're doing it to develop clarity, to
to to maintain perspective, basically.
That's what you're doing it.
And same again, this is like from the
point of view of practicing the Dhamma
and the Buddha's teaching, but even if
you just want to
live a wholesome skillful for life
as a you know, a normal lay person not
interested in some, you know, renouncing
the world that has family and job, still
it's going to help you.
It's certainly going to going to
strengthen you and develop your mind to
deal with anything else that comes your
way in a lay life. And there are a lot
of things coming people's way.
Lots of pressure, lots of stress, lots
of burden.
Initial response is you just deal by any
means necessary.
But if you start dealing it rightly
through the right perspective,
restraint, and virtue,
it's going to make things more difficult
in the beginning, but in the long run,
it just creates this resilience that
nothing else can match.
That's the definition of wisdom,
basically. Obviously, you can have it to different
Obviously, you can have it to different
degrees, but
having perspective on yourself in in a
situation, not just being absorbed and pulled by
not just being absorbed and pulled by
the immediacy of a situation,
and which usually results in being quite
uh reactionary.
Situations like this, I react like this,
just like an animal.
And it's also useful before. Like, if
people The sooner people start thinking
like this, better. As in thinking in
terms of self-reflecting and and really
questioning themselves all the time.
The sooner, the better, because you
would have committed less in life,
as in started a family, and now you have
people that you have to look after, and
so on, that you can't just turn your
back on.
Uh but even then, it's not too late,
cuz there is no end to a human
proliferation in the world, to the
proliferation of sensuality in the wrong
view, and lack of restraint. There is no
end to that.
The only end to that is self-reflection.
That will then prevent you from from
proliferating carelessly
through greed and ill will and wrong
views and hatred and whatnot.
It's true protection, really. It is.
You can't
Taking up responsibility is a true
protection. Yeah. Yeah. For yourself.
Yeah. Yeah. For yourself.
Going getting into a group or certain
nationality or identity.
That's the opposite. Yeah, that's the
opposite. That's when you have already
disowned your your responsibility, then
you find affirmation in that act by
identifying with the greater group.
That's just obscures it even further.
The fact that you already covered up
your personal responsibility for your
personal existence and your personal
choices. And then it's just intoxicating. That's
And then it's just intoxicating. That's
like the masses, you know.
And even things that you wouldn't have
necessarily done on a personal level,
if you were with yourself, questioning
yourself, you would have you you do it in a group.
you would have you you do it in a group.
Because again, he's just got all
absorbed in this impersonal they, as the
as Heidegger would have been talking
about. The now is just acting as this complete
The now is just acting as this complete
protection and you can do whatever you
want. That's like mob, definition of a
mob mentality.
When you know these things are wrong and
you wouldn't have done them if you were
on your own or with with somebody else
who is not like
But now it's just a mob is intoxicating.
And why it's intoxicating? Because it's
just extension
of of of complete lack of
well, of complete cover up of your
personal responsibility.
And then you just do stuff that you were
not supposed to for that very sake. It's
going to be quite inviting to do it.
Hey, let's smash these windows and break
this. Not because they done anything to
us or up have any game. No, just because
you're not supposed to do it. And if you
do it, you'll be responsible for it. But
now we're in a mob, who cares? They
can't get me. And then you do it.
It's like the ultimate non-restraint.
And the ultimate contradiction.
Cuz you can't really you can only cover
up your responsibility, which means
through every single act of covering up
your personal responsibility, you
reaffirm that personal responsibility
because that's the very reason of your
actions of covering it up.
Hence as Sartre would define it as bad
faith or or or inauthenticity.
or or or inauthenticity.
But you carry it. You carry it in the
heart of everything you do.
It's almost like if you want to make
your society strong, you have to do
your work. Exactly. Yeah, society will
be
the strong society would be a result of
personally developed individuals.
Developed in the sense of accepting
responsibility and gaining perspective
and account of it as in developing
wisdom. The result would be a strong society, a
The result would be a strong society, a
resilient society, a just society.
Society that has a right perspective on
things. Society that's quite aligned
with good is good and bad is bad.
Cuz that's what I mean.
It's that It's that that contradiction
at the existential level that's bad.
That's why bad things are bad.
So, if now through your own self not not
through adopting like Dharma or
Christianity or anything, just through
that self-reflection of not tolerating
existential contradiction,
not covering up your responsibility for
your own choices,
maintaining perspective through constant
self-questioning, basically that will already result in
basically that will already result in
you aligning yourself with good action.
Even if you don't necessarily know it or
have have not accepted it as a some sort
of external set of values.
And then if everybody were to start
doing that to
respective degree as much as they're
capable, it would reflect on the society
as a whole.
Cuz there's no society without
individuals. Individuals precede society.
Individuals precede society.
But obviously it's much more
um
inspiring, so to speak, and it certainly
quite requires less work to just
identify with the impersonal notion of
society and by doing so
and by doing so
enable yourself even further to cover up
your own responsibility that you have
been avoiding. Because if you were
transparent to begin with, you wouldn't
have identified yourself cuz you realize
what a contradiction that is. You can't
be they.
No matter how much you're absorbed in a
in a greater cause and whatnot, you
cannot step outside of your point of
view ever.
You're completely confined to that
perspective. Yet you say no, this is not me, this is
Yet you say no, this is not me, this is
a greater good, this is a greater
greater service, a greater a group
greater group basically.
But if you really want to contribute to
a group, you do so from the inside as in
every single individual.
You can't abstract the group
as if it's independent of individuals.
It's it's basically an attempt at a
shortcut. Hey, let's let's create a philosophy or
Hey, let's let's create a philosophy or
a policy or or a political system that
will be dealing
with group as such.
Putting individuals second.
And that was the definition of communism
or certainly one of the principles,
maybe not a definition, but
but it's like, okay, well,
you theorized the perfection of a group
and then you try Okay, so in order to
maintain this perfect image of a group,
we'll be sort of attacking individuals
and dealing with them because we want to
And all you're doing is maintaining your
own notion, your own perspective what
you think group is.
That's what I mean, you can't step
outside of your personal point of view
ever.
And if you do, it's in order to cover it
up. Hence the group identity, group
Hence the group identity, group
politics,
anything mob mob mentality,
nationalism, anything, religion,
if it's done for those reasons and it is
usually. You wouldn't be stepping outside of your
You wouldn't be stepping outside of your
group if you're not running away from
your own self self-responsibility.
You wouldn't need a group.
I wonder how society would look if
everyone took personal responsibility.
Well, as I said, it would be it would
probably be much much more aligned with
principles of good and principles of
bad. People would have that on on an average
People would have that on on an average
sort of an average person would have a
good would have a good sort of judgment of
would have a good sort of judgment of
what's good, what's bad. As in like it
would have a notion of it why good is
good, bad is bad.
So, you could see our modern society how
far it's removed from that.
Like people would know and value certain
things, but that's far from having an
having that's far from saying that they
understood those things.
That's why the Buddha was talking about
the just leader back in the day. The
righteous king.
Clearly has developed knowledge of good
is good, bad is bad and then he wouldn't
be just taking and conquering. He's
giving back. So, basically people can
have a certain
certain um quality to their life.
Not just exploitation for the sake of
personal gain.
And because of that then people start
valuing that and then they start doing
the same cuz the king is just there the
just ones.
And they don't blame gratuitously or try
to avoid their own responsibility. Why?
Cuz basically that's how people already
are acting responsibly and so on then
you would really stand out.
That's a decline of society basically
when when sensuality and avoiding of
responsibility become a norm.
And you realize it like in schools for
example when you were growing up when I
was growing up.
I mean we were taught everything and
nothing. But
But
has any of us ever been taught taught in
our schools elementary or higher
like you know, the the value of
patience, the value of sense restraint,
the value of being able to say no to
yourself. To be
No. Everything if if you got any of that, it
Everything if if you got any of that, it
was circumstantial.
And I think that's quite universal. I
don't think like the whole notion of
school back in you know, the days of the
ancient Greece was to part sort of to
enable people to go through their life
more wisely.
To be able to deal to to basically to to
create a perspective for them that will
then create in a better life for them.
And you realize today there's there's
none of that. Perspective? No.
You're just being thrown information
by the teacher.
If you parrot the information back, you
passed. If you don't, very little
understanding of it is actually
encouraged. Why? Because people are
teaching haven't understood it
themselves. You're just going through a curriculum.
You're just going through a curriculum.
So then you can't be surprised that then
the value on the level of society is
just a mirroring
personal values.
Which is just following your desires,
getting what you want whenever you want
it, however you want it, not being
responsible, blaming others.
It's kind of a norm nowadays.
But it's impossible a perfect society.
It's impossible, yeah. Yeah. A perfect
society would be basically a Sangha of
Arhats, but that wouldn't be a society
anymore.
That doesn't mean of course that
a person should not be um aiming
at perfection internally.
Personally. Cuz aiming at 100% will at least mirror
Cuz aiming at 100% will at least mirror
20% into society of good. The essence of
the goal
other people can learn from.
Yeah, that's not the goal. It's not to
perfect society.
No. No, that would be basically like
think of society as um
as like a generated image on a kind of
operating individuals.
And it's that operation of those
individuals, their actions, that's the
problem. Generating image of it is just a symptom
Generating image of it is just a symptom
of a problem. So you could see the you
could basically see the problems of
individuals by looking at the problems
of society.
It would just be a more general
projection of it.
By you trying to deal with the problems
of society at the level of society, it's
like trying to deal with a projection of
a problem, not the actual problem.
That's why it's it's you can use it to
learn from it
to to maintain perspective, but the
problem is undone on the personal level
through that responsibility and
self-reflection and questioning and
natural virtue that will come out of it.
Then the projection will change. You'll
be projecting those things, not the lack
of those things.
that. Communism never tried it. How about
Communism never tried it. How about
socialism? We'll try it. Democ-
democracy won't Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly. Or let's
let's replace this this kind of um
arrangement of society with another
arrangement, with a different system.
But again, that's missing the point.
That's just basically fighting over
types of projection.
Or trying fighting over over ways you
should be dealing with projections.
But you're not uprooting the actual
problem that is being projected.
And again, that attitude itself is a
projection of the individual attitude
towards your own problems.
Like when people suffer, when people
experience difficulties,
they don't necessarily look
into themselves as in is this a
projection of my attitude or my actions?
No, they want to manage it. They want to
manage the problem. They want to remove
the problem. They want to get rid of the
problem. So that's what I mean. Everything on the
So that's what I mean. Everything on the
level of society
is a projection of the
from the level of individuals,
whichever prevails.
And that in itself
is already a projection of an individual
attitude that they have that people have
in regard to their own problems and
suffering.
Oh, I have a problem. Well, who caused
it? Well, if it's me, okay, well, then I'll
Well, if it's me, okay, well, then I'll
I'll either apologize or whatever. Let's
pretend it never happened. All these
things are management of the problem that has
are management of the problem that has
already arisen.
Yeah, you can do that, but that's not
uprooting the problem. Don't confuse the
two. Uprooting of the problem is then
reflecting further and saying, "Okay,
but will I in the future then cause the
same issue for myself through my
careless actions, for example?
Or will I be able to prevent it?
How can I prevent it?
And that's that's the true definition of
learning from your own mistakes, like
trial and error.
Where you want to look not just to deal
with this particular issue
that has arisen,
but to basically extrapolate a principle
that you can discern that can then help
you not make the same mistake
in the future. And if that's your
attitude towards your own personal
existence and actions and responsibility
and choices and so on,
and there's the attitude of other people
as well, that will be reflected in
society then.
Or at least not
the larger society, but your your
family. Well, of course, yeah. Yeah, certainly,
Well, of course, yeah. Yeah, certainly,
yeah. Yeah, it's
individual, then the family, then the
smaller group, whatever, then obviously.
But But it all trickles down.
Like a Like a Like a stream on a
mountain top that's feeding down
lower streams that are feeding down
lower rivers that are feeding down lower
lakes and and and other rivers, and then
eventually feeding down the seas and so
on. If you dry it up at the top or if you
If you dry it up at the top or if you
remove the pollution from it at the top,
eventually even the sea will cease to be
polluted. But if you're just trying to deal with
But if you're just trying to deal with
the level of on the level of the sea
without addressing the source of the
pollution, well, you're fighting a losing battle. Mhm.